Institute for Software Research Carnegie Mellon University 5000 Forbes Ave Pittsburgh, PA 15213

School of Computer Science

Phone: +1 (412) 268-2748 heather.miller@cs.cmu.edu http://heather.miller.am

HEATHER MILLER

Citizenship

USA

Research Interests Concurrent, distributed, eventually-consistent (edge computing), data-centric, and data-intensive (big data) programming, from the perspective of programming languages. I work on both theoretical ideas & implementations typically in/for the Scala programming language. My goal is to reduce the burden of building distributed systems.

Education

EPFL, Lausanne, Switzerland

2009 - 2015

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Advisor: Martin Odersky

2011 - 2015

University of Miami, Coral Gables, FL

2006 - 2009

2004 - 2006

BSEE in Electrical Engineering, Audio Engineering, with honors, May 2009

Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, New York, NY

Employment

Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA, USA

8/2018 -

Assistant Professor

School of Computer Science, Institute for Software Research

Northeastern University, Boston, MA, USA

9/2016 - 7/2018

Assistant Clinical Professor

College of Computer and Information Science

Scala Center, EPFL, Lausanne, Switzerland

10/2015 - 7/2018

Executive Director, Research Scientist

Founded a new not-for-profit center dedicated to research, open source development, and education surrounding the Scala programming language.

Databricks, Berkeley, CA, USA

8/2014 - 11/2014

Research Intern

Supervisor: Matei Zaharia

Integrated Scala Pickling, our framework for fast, boilerplate-free, extensible serialization focused on distributed programming (OOPSLA'13), into Spark. Developed new function-passing programming model and framework, can be thought of as a generalization of Spark/MapReduce programming model (JFP'18).

Teaching Experience (Classroom) Co-Instructor,

17-356: Software Engineering for Startups

Spring 2019 & Spring 2020 Carnegie Mellon

Instructor, Designer,	Spring 2018
CS4240: Large-Scale Parallel Data Processing	Northeastern
Instructor, Designer,	Fall 2016
CS7680: Programming Models for Distributed Computation	Northeastern
Co-Instructor, Co-Designer, (with Viktor Kunčak & Martin Odersky)	Spring 2016
CS 206: Parallelism & Concurrency	EPFL
Co-Instructor, Co-Designer, (with Viktor Kunčak & Martin Odersky)	Spring 2015
CS 212: Reactive Programming & Parallelism	EPFL
(Lead) Teaching Assistant,	Fall 2011-2014
CS 201: Functional Programming	EPFL
Instructor, Designer, Big Data Analysis with Scala and Spark	2017 -

Teaching Experience (MOOCs) Instructor, Designer, Big Data Analysis with Scala and Spark2017Popular Coursera MOOC on big data analysis using Spark.Coursera

- Designed lectures and produced lecture videos. Designed exercises and developed cloud-hosted automated graders.
- Between March-November 2017, over 120,000 registered learners.

Lead, Scala Specialization (mini-degree)

2015 -

Responsible for EPFL's offering of a Scala *mini-degree* on Coursera.

Coursera

Assembled offering of 4 Scala MOOCs, topped off with a capstone
project. Taught and produced 1 course in the specialization and
managed the development of the remaining 3 courses and the project.

Lead, Functional Programming Principles in Scala Popular Coursera MOOC on functional programming in Scala. 2012 – 2014 Coursera

- Lead teaching staff member, organized a team of graduate students, managed content production, designed course exercises with cloud-hosted grading, production of lecture videos, etc.
- >400,000 learners across iterations & largest completion rate for a course its size (~19%)

Book Distributed Programming

MIT Press 2018/2019

Heather Miller, Nat Dempkowski, James Larisch, Christopher Meiklejohn, and Philipp Haller

A textbook about the building blocks we use to build distributed systems. These range from the small, RPC, futures, actors, to the large; systems built up of these components like MapReduce and Spark. We explore issues and concerns central to distributed systems like consistency, availability, and fault tolerance, from the lens of the programming models and frameworks that the programmer uses to build these systems. *Source (draft)*

Publications: Journals A Reduction Semantics for Direct-Style Asynchronous Observables

JLAMP 2019

Philipp Haller, Heather Miller

Journal of Logical and Algebraic Methods in Programming, Volume 105, p75-111.

A Programming Model and Foundation for Lineage-Based Distributed Computation

JFP 2018

Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Normen Müller *Journal of Functional Programming, Volume 28, e7. Special Issue: Programming Languages for Big Data*

Publications: Conferences

Partisan: Scaling the Distributed Actor Runtime

USENIX ATC 2019

Christopher Meiklejohn, Heather Miller, Peter Alvaro

USENIX Annual Technical Conference

Scala Implicits are Everywhere: A Large-Scale Study of the Use of Implicits in the Wild

OOPSLA 2019

Filip Křikava, Heather Miller, Jan Vitek

ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Object Oriented Programming, Systems,

Languages and Applications

Simplicitly: Foundations and Applications of Implicit Function Types POPL 2018

Martin Odersky, Olivier Blanvillain, Fengyun Liu, Aggelos Biboudis

Heather Miller, Sandro Stucki

ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages

Function Passing: A Model for Typed, Distributed Functional Programming

SPLASH 2016

Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Normen Müller, Joceyln Boullier ACM SIGPLAN International Symposium on New Ideas, New Paradigms, and Reflections on Programming & Software

Spores: A Type-Based Foundation for Closures in the Age of Concurrency and Distribution

ECOOP 2014

Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Martin Odersky European Conference on Object Oriented Programming

Functional Programming For All! Scaling a MOOC for Students And Professionals Alike

ICSE 2014

Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Lukas Rytz, Martin Odersky ACM SIGSOFT International Conference on Software Engineering

Instant Pickles: Generating Object-Oriented Pickler Combinators for Fast and Extensible Serialization

OOPSLA 2013

Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Eugene Burmako, Martin Odersky ACM SIGPLAN Conference on Object Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages and Applications

Publications: Workshops

Checking-in on Network Functions

ANRW 2019

Zeeshan Lakhani, Heather Miller

ACM/IRTF Applied Networking Research Workshop

Towards a Solution to the Red Wedding Problem

USENIX HotEdge 2018

Christopher Meiklejohn, Heather Miller, Zeeshan Lakhani USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing

Distributed Programming via Safe Closure Passing

PLACES 2015

Philipp Haller, Heather Miller

Programming Language Approaches to Communication

and Concurrency Centric Systems

RAY: Integrating Rx and Async for Direct-Style Reactive Streams

REM 2013

Philipp Haller, Heather Miller

ACM SPLASH Workshop on Reactivity, Events and Modularity

FlowPools: A Lock-Free Deterministic Concurrent

LCPC 2012

Dataflow Abstraction

Aleksandar Prokopec, Heather Miller, Tobias Schlatter,

Philipp Haller, Martin Odersky

International Workshop on Languages and Compilers for Parallel Computing

Invited to Revised Selected Papers on the 25th International Workshop on Languages and Compilers for Parallel Computing, Lecture Notes in Computer Science, Vol. 7760, 2013

Tools and Frameworks for Big Learning in Scala: Leveraging the Language for High Productivity and Performance

BigLearn 2011

Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Martin Odersky

NIPS Workshop on Parallel and Large-Scale Machine Learning

Parallelizing Machine Learning – Functionally: A Framework and Abstractions for Parallel Graph Processing

Scala 2011

Philipp Haller, Heather Miller

Scala Workshop

Submitted/In Preparation

Monotonicity Types

Kevin Clancy, Heather Miller, Christopher Meiklejohn

The Essence of Coordination-Free Distributed Computation

Christopher Meiklejohn, Kevin Clancy, Heather Miller

Selected Tech Reports

The Function Passing Model: Types, Proofs, and Semantics

May 2016

Philipp Haller, Normen Müller, Heather Miller

Specialising Parsers for Queries

April 2016

Manohar Jonnalagedda, Jorge Vicente Cantero, Heather Miller, Martin Odersky

Improving Human-Compiler Interaction Through Customizable

December 2014

Type Feedback Hubert Plociniczak, Heather Miller, Martin Odersky	
Self-Assembly: Lightweight Language Extension and Datatype Generic Programming, All-in-One! Heather Miller, Philipp Haller, Bruno C. d. S. Oliveira	2014
Spores, Formally December Heather Miller, Philipp Haller	2013
FlowPools: A Lock-Free Deterministic Concurrent Dataflow Abstraction – Proofs Aleksandar Prokopec, Heather Miller, Philipp Haller	2012
General Chair and/or Program Chair:	
Curry On (Curry On) 2015, 2016, 2017, 2018,	2019
ICSE Software Engineering in Practice (ICSE SEIP)	2022
Workshop on Principles and Practice of Consistency for Distributed Data (PaPoC)	2019
Trends in Functional Programming in Education (TFPIE)	2018
Scala Symposium (Scala) 2013, 2014,	•
Programming Models & Languages for Distributed Computation (PMLDC) 2016,	2017
Organizing Committee Member:	
Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages & Applications (OOPSLA)	2018
European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming (ECOOP) 2015 -	
Program Committee Member:	
USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Edge Computing (USENIX HotEdge)	2020
Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages & Applications (OOPSLA)	2019
European Conference on Object-Oriented Programming (ECOOP)	2019
Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages (POPL)	2019
International Conference on Functional Programming (ICFP)	2018
Off the Beaten Track (OBT)	2018
Object-Oriented Programming, Systems, Languages & Applications (OOPSLA) Scala Symposium (Scala)	2017
Symposium on Trends in Functional Programming (TFP)	2016 2016
Software Language Engineering (SLE)	2016
Symposium on Applied Computing (SAC)	2016
Programming Language Evolution (PLE)	2015
	2015
External Review Committee Member:	
PLDI 2020, PLDI 2018, ECOOP 2016, ECOOP 2013, Scala 2013	
Artifact Evaluation Committee: POPL 2015	
ScalaBridge Organizer Organizer of free full-day workshops on the weekends aimed at teaching women	

and underrepresented minorities in computing how to think computationally and

ScalaBridge Chapters: Basel (CH), Zürich (CH), Copenhagen (DK), Boston (US).

External Service

Diversity &

how to program in Scala.

Outreach

$\overline{}$				_					
()	n	Δ	n	S	\sim	11	r	_	0
v	v	c		J	v	u	ш	u	C

Scala Programming Language, member of the Scala team

2011 -

- Scala Spores (Scala Improvement Proposal SIP-21), project lead novel type-based abstraction for using closures safely in concurrent and distributed environments
- Scala Pickling, *project lead* novel framework for fast, boilerplate-free, extensible serialization. Adopted by sbt, the most widely-used build tool for Scala. Popular open-source project on GitHub with >820 stars & dozens of contributors
- Scala Futures & Promises (Scala Improvement Proposal SIP-14), *team member* unified non-blocking concurrency substrate for Scala, Akka, Play, and others
- Scala Documentation, creator, writer, lead maintainer
 a central website for community-driven documentation for
 the Scala programming language and core libraries
- Scaladoc, co-maintainer documentation tool for Scala's official API documentation

Honors

ACM SIGPLAN Programming Languages Software Award (for Scala)	2019
US National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship	2011 - 2014
EPFL Outstanding Teaching Award	2012
EPFL Computer Science Fellowship	2009 - 2010
Most Outstanding Audio Engineering Student, University of Miami	2009
Most Outstanding Eta Kappa Nu Student, University of Miami	2009
Information Technology Scholarship, University of Miami	2006 - 2009
John Farina Family Scholarship, University of Miami	2006 - 2009
Eta Kappa Nu	2008
Tau Beta Pi	2008
SMART US Department of Defense Scholarship Alternate	2007
Cooper Union Full Tuition Scholarship	2004 - 2006

Selected Talks

The Times They Are a-Changin': A Data-Driven Portrait of
New Trends in How We Build Software, Open Source,
& What Even is Entry-Level Now
Oakland, CA, USA. November 14, 2019

Scale By the Bay 2019
(keynote)

Scala Implicits are Everywhere: A Large-Scale Study of the Use
Athens, Greece. October 24, 2019

We're Building On Hollowed Foundations: Worrying Trends in Open Source and What We Can Actually Do About It (keynote)
Genoa, Italy. April 4, 2019

Towards Language Support for Distributed Systems
London, UK. November 9, 2018

Code Mesh 2018

(invited)

What Happened to Distributed Programming Languages? SPLASH-I 2018

Boston, MA, USA. November 6, 2018

(invited)

Towards Language Support for Distributed Systems St. Louis, MO, USA. September 27, 2018

Strange Loop 2018

I'm a Young Assistant Professor: AMA. + Heather's Unsolicited Advice About Grad School

PLMW 2018 (invited)

St. Louis, MO, USA. September 23, 2018

We're Building On Hollowed Foundations: Worrying Trends in Open Source and What You Can Actually Do About It

Lambda Days 2018 (keynote)

Krakow, Poland. February 22, 2018

The Dramatic Consequences of the Open Source Revolution: Unrecognized Challenges & Some Modest Attempts at Solutions in Scala

Devoxx 2017 (invited)

Paris, France. April 7, 2017

The Dramatic Consequences of the Open Source Revolution & How the Scala Center Hopes to Help

Scala Exchange 2016 (keynote)

London, UK. December 9, 2016

Function Passing: A Model for Typed, Distributed Functional Programming

SPLASH 2016

Amsterdam, The Netherlands. November 2, 2016

Introducing the Scala Center

Scala Days 2016

New York, NY, US. May 10, 2016 & Berlin, Germany. June 16, 2016

(keynote)

(total ~1700 attendees)

Function Passing Style: Typed, Distributed **Functional Programming**

Strange Loop 2014

St. Louis, MO, USA. September 19, 2014

Spores: A Type-Based Foundation for Closures in the Age of

ECOOP 2014

Concurrency and Distribution Uppsala, Sweden. August 1, 2014

ICSE 2014

Functional Programming For All! Scaling a MOOC for Students and Professionals Alike

Hyderabad, India. June 4, 2014

Academese to English: Scala's Type System, Dependent Types and What It Means To You

NEScala 2014

New York, NY, USA. March 1, 2014

Instant Pickles: Generating Object-Oriented Pickler Combinators for Fast and Extensible Serialization

OOPSLA 2013

Indianapolis, IN, USA. October 30, 2013

PL Abstractions for Distributed Programming:

Indiana University (invited)

Pickle Your Spores!

Bloomington, IN, USA. October 25, 2013

Spores: Distributable Functions in Scala St. Louis, MO, USA. September 19, 2013

Strange Loop 2013

Open Issues in Dataflow Programming

Montpellier, France. July 1, 2013

LaME 2013 (invited)

Scala as a Research Tool

Montpellier, France. July 1, 2013

ECOOP 2013 Tutorial

On Pickles & Spores: Improving Scala's Support for Distributed Programming

New York, NY, USA. June 12, 2013

ScalaDays 2013

Futures & Promises in Scala 2.10

Philadelphia, PA, USA. April 2, 2013

PhillyETE 2013 (invited)

I am also a frequent speaker in industry, at industrial conferences, developer "meet-ups", and everything in between. Some such events include:

Scala Italy (9/2018, Florence, Italy), LxScala (6/2018, Lisbon, Portugal), Open Source Summit (12/2017, Paris, France), Scala World (9/2017, Lake District, UK), LxScala (5/2017, Lisbon, Portugal), Lambda Days (2/2017, Krakow, Poland), PhillyETE (4/2016, Philadelphia, USA), Code Mesh (11/2015, London, UK), Scalar (4/2015, Warsaw, Poland), f(by) (11/2014, Minsk, Belarus), SF Scala (11/2014, SF, USA), Scalapeño (9/2014, Tel Aviv, Israel), SoundCloud TechTalks (7/2014, Berlin, Germany), Scala Days (6/2014, Berlin, Germany), NEScala (3/2014, NYC, USA), amongst others.

External Activities

Scalawags Monthly Podcast, co-host

2014 - 2016

Students Supervised Matthew Weidner, TBD

2019 -

PhD thesis Carnegie Mellon

Zeeshan Lakhani, TBD2018 -PhD thesisCarnegie Mellon

Christopher Meiklejohn, TBD 2018 – PhD thesis Carnegie Mellon

Joceyln Boullier, Evaluating the Efficiacy of the Function Passing Model 2/2016 – 8/2016 M.Sc. thesis EPFL

Jorge Vicente Cantero, *Implementing the Function Passing Model* 2/2016 – 6/2016 B.Sc. thesis EPFL

Thaddée Yann Tyl, Learning Scala Style 2/2013 – 6/2013 M.Sc. thesis EPFL

References

Martin Odersky, Professor École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne

2 +41 21 693 68 63

⊠ martin.odersky@epfl.ch

Matei Zaharia, Assistant Professor *Stanford University*

a +1-510-610-0001

⊠ matei@cs.stanford.edu

Matthias Felleisen, Trustee Professor

Northeastern University

a +1-617-373-2085

⊠ matthias@ccs.neu.edu

Philipp Haller, Associate Professor KTH Royal Institute of Technology

a +46 70 738 28 43

⊠ phaller@kth.se